<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Short surveigh of the grand case of the present ministry whether they may lawfully subscribe and declare as by the late Act of uniformity is required, and the several cases thence arising, especially about the covenant / by some conformable non-conformists.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 98 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37367</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D64</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14722</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12207312</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12207312</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56201</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A37367)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56201)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 888:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Short surveigh of the grand case of the present ministry whether they may lawfully subscribe and declare as by the late Act of uniformity is required, and the several cases thence arising, especially about the covenant / by some conformable non-conformists.</title>
                  <author>M. D.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>47 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Work signed by M.D., S.C., I.F., O.R. and A.T.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fullwood, Francis, d. 1693. --  Grand case of the present ministry.</term>
               <term>Church of England. --  Book of common prayer --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56201:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56201:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SHORT SURVEIGH OF THE Grand Caſe of the preſent MINISTRY <hi>WHETHER</hi> They may Lawfully Subſcribe and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare as by the late Act of <hi>Uniformity</hi> is required.</p>
            <p>AND The ſeveral Caſes thence ariſing, eſpecially about the COVENANT.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Some Conformable Non-Conformiſts</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Pet. 4.19.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Wherefore let them that ſuffer according to the Will of God, commit the keeping of their Soules to him in well doing as to a Faithful Creator.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed, in the Year, 1663.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:56201:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56201:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ur Condition is ſad, and the more ſad, by reaſon of thoſe Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere Cenſures which Sober, and Learned men paſs upon us, as if peeviſhneſs and groundleſs Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puloſity were the only cauſe of our preſent Croſs.</p>
            <p>Do we need to Appeal to God that we love our ſelves? We conceive Natural Men ſhould beleive us without it; And if we may be beleived therein, can it be ſuppoſed we would not willingly receive ſatisfaction to our Doubts?</p>
            <p>Let us tell thee we have read what hath been written to offer us ſatisfaction, but we find none.</p>
            <p>The Grand Caſe of the preſent Miniſtry hath made the faireſt proffer, as profeſſedly written for our ſake to help the pinch of our
<pb facs="tcp:56201:3"/>Caſe; but yet it hath alſo failed our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations and left us on the Rack of our doubts, or rather Shipwrack of our Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions.</p>
            <p>Leaſt we ſhould by a ſinful Silence juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy the ſevere Cenſures which paſs upon us; We have adventured to digeſt our diſſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factions in the enſuing Tract, that our haeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancie in the conformity expected from us may be viſible, and if poſſible remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
            <p>But now we have ſtated our doubts, we are in doubt of ſome ſevere moderation by the Interpoſition of Authority, yet why do we doubt? did ever the Engliſh Proteſtant <hi>Genius</hi> determine a Crime in a ſober Diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation? We affirme nothing, only urge what ſticketh with us as the Remora to that Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation which is expected from us.</p>
            <p>In the following Tract it might be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected we ſhould have ſaid ſomthing to the Caſe of Reordination, but we are not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in concerned; and our Reverend Caſuiſt ſaith nothing but turneth us over to Mr. <hi>Humphry</hi> whoſe ſad experience of the Fact
<pb facs="tcp:56201:3"/>he retracts, and yet defends, doth add no lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to the real weakneſs of his Argumentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on that point; we could tell thee we have ſeen two ſeveral Anſwers to his laſt piece on this Subject, which are ſmothered leaſt their appearance ſhould break their bruiſed Reed, and add Affliction to him whom God hath grieved. Unto this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe with which we deal is added ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations about admitting ſome inexpedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies, for the neceſſity of our Miniſtry un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this (which we think ſufficiently obnox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ious to exception) we have ſaid nothing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we have admitted, and could admit many inexpediencies for the Liberty of our Miniſtry, and our Conſcience doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive formal, poſitive, and ſpecial ſin in what is required from us; So that until the Act be acquitted from Sin, the Caſe of Neceſſity and expediency cannot take place in our Souls.</p>
            <p>Through the whole we wiſh it may be obſerved we may appear as Apologiſts for our non-complyance with what is required, rather then as Antagoniſts to what is affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med:
<pb facs="tcp:56201:4"/>We have therefore propounded our own diſſatisfactions, rather then diſputed againſt what is urged by the Reverend Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the <hi>Grand Caſe of the preſent Miniſtry,</hi> to whom our doubts are directed.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:56201:4"/>
            <head>A SHOHT SVRVEIGH OF THE <hi>GRAND CASE</hi> OF THE Preſent Miniſtry, VVhether they may Declare and Subſcribe as is required in the Act for <hi>Uniformity,</hi> in an Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the Author of the <hi>Grand Caſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="preface">
               <head>The Preface.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Reverend Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>VVE, ſome of your Brethren, in compaſſion to whom you have been pleaſed to compoſe and publiſh your Candid and elaborate Tract, Entituled the <hi>Grand Caſe of the preſent Miniſtry.</hi> Having ſeriouſly conſidered the ſame, as being therein concerned; after ſome ſilence, have aſſumed the boldneſs of addreſſing theſe Lines unto you, thankfully to acknowledge your Zeal, Sobriety and Charity, therein expreſſed; and modeſtly to ſignify to you, it hath not made on us that Impreſſion, nor produced that effect, you might rationally promiſe to your ſelf, and our ſelves can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but obſerve it hath effected in many others, Yet, Sir,</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:56201:5"/>
               <p n="2">2. We muſt and do acknowledge your Grave and ſerious Preface, moſt truly ſtating the Caſe of ſelf-created Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, and the ſinfulneſs thereof; hath ſeized on our Spirits with no mean force.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Truly, Sir, we are not a little troubled to apprehend men, yea wiſe and learned men reprehend us as <hi>felones de ſe,</hi> we have eſteemed life ſweet, and are preſſed to perſue the preſervation thereof, not only in reference to our ſelves, but alſo in reference to our Wives and Children; ſome of them can make our hearts ake, crying for the bread of our late loſt Benefices, and ſo keep us from any proud, profuſe, contempt of the comfortable livelyhoods we did enjoy.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The thoughts of being <hi>fures de ſe,</hi> do much terrifie us, we are convinced we are not our own, our Perſons, our Parts, our Miniſtry, are Gods, his Churches, and the Kings, from whence we may not withhold the ſame, for a moment unleſs ſuperſeded by ſome ſin, which we dare not commit and break through for the greateſt good.</p>
               <p n="5">5. You make our hearts tremble when <hi>Boanerges</hi> like you pronounce us, <hi>Proditors de ſe,</hi> and that in the great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments of our Miniſtry, dearer to us then all our lives, as committed to us for the ſalvation of pretious Souls, many more then our own, or thoſe of our own houſeholds.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The conſideration of theſe things, have conſtrained us to preſs upon you, and to preſent to you our diſſatisfaction (and the grounds thereof) in your ſerious explications of, and expoſtulations with us, in the matters which appear to you the <hi>Grand Cauſe</hi> of our preſent caſe, to which we beg your leave to paſs with all plainneſs and brevity, that if you can convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cingly reply to it, we may bleſs God for you, as our Redeemer out of our preſent dark and comfortleſs condition.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:56201:5"/>
               <head>The Grand Caſe.</head>
               <head type="sub">VVhether it be Lawful to declare, as is required in the late Act, Intituled an Act for Uniformity of Publick Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers.</head>
               <p>SIR,<note place="margin">Pa. 1ſt.</note> your book doth profeſs to deal with ſuch <hi>Who could Conform, but could not declare and ſubſcribe what is required in, and by the Act of Uniformity;</hi> but you wholly paſs by thoſe men, who are <hi>againſt the uſe of the Common Prayer Book:</hi> We Sir, muſt needs confeſs our ſelves, to be Miniſters of the Ranck with whom you deale; yet we muſt profeſs we ſhould rejoyce to ſee ſome Satisfactory diſcourſe directed to the latter, many of whom we know to be men of Learning and ſobriety, faithful Subjects to the King, and profitable Miniſters in, and to the Church of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Theſe men we do diſcerne to ſtumble, at a <hi>Liturgie, gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally</hi> (throughout all Acts in Miniſtration of Gods Ordinances,) and <hi>Excluſively</hi> (ſo that men muſt be tyed to thoſe forms, and none other.) <hi>Impoſed,</hi> becauſe they conceive the <hi>Modifying Gods Ordinances in, and to the Church by perſonal Miniſterial Gifts, is the formal Act in and by which they muſt fulfill the Miniſtrey to them committed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Theſe men are, Sir, of Age ſufficient to ſpeak for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and do complain they have ſpoken, and are Anſwered by <hi>Rigour</hi> without <hi>Reaſon,</hi> we ſhall therefore leave them to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and being ſingled out by you, we ſhall adventure to ſpeak for our ſelves, becauſe for our ſake it is you have been pleaſed to take ſo great pains.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Sir, we take it for granted, you conceive the Declarations required from us, to be Tantamount to an Oath, they are to be Solemnly made in the Congregation, by Miniſters <hi>qua</hi> Miniſters of the Goſpel, in which <hi>virbum ſacerdotis</hi> is the Sacred Rivet of that Obligation, which reſulteth from ſuch Declaration, to our Conſcience in the ſight of God, and his Church.</p>
               <p n="5">5. On this Conſideration, we preſume you will have Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56201:6"/>table apprehenſions of our preſent Haeſiſtancie as to the <hi>Subſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>publiſhing</hi> ſuch Declarations, for it is a <hi>Snare to devoure holy things, and after Vows to make enquiry,</hi> and we ſhall in unbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſed Judgements weigh your grounds on which you determine this Caſe, affirmatively moving in our Obſervation, according to the Method of your Argumentation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="declarations">
               <head>The Declarations are theſe two, by you truely Tranſcribed.</head>
               <div type="declaration">
                  <head>The Firſt is this.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>J. A. B.</hi> DO here declrae my unfeigned aſſent, and conſent to all and every thing contained and preſcribed in,<note place="margin">Pa. 2.3.</note> and by the Book Entituled, <hi>The Book of Common Prayer,</hi> and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Sacraments, and other Rites, and Cerimonies of the the Church, according to the uſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Pſalter or Pſalmes of <hi>David,</hi> pointed as they are to be Sung, or ſaid in Churches, and the forme, or manner of making, Ordaining, or Conſecrating of Biſhops, Preiſts or Decons.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="declaration">
                  <head>The Second is this.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>J. A. B.</hi> DO Declare that it is not lawful upon pretence what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever to take Arms againſt the King, and that I do abhor that Traiterous Poſition of taking Armes, by his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity againſt his perſon, or againſt thoſe Commiſſioned by him, and that I will conforme to the Liturgie of the Church of <hi>England</hi> as it is now Eſtabliſhed by Law; and I do declare that I do hold there lies no obligation upon me, or any other perſon from the Oath commonly called the <hi>Solemn League and Covenant,</hi> to endeavour any Change or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of Government, either in Church or State, and that the ſame was in its ſelf an unlawful Oath, and impoſed on the Subjects of this Realme, againſt the known Laws, and Liberties of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theſeare the Declarations which you affirme may be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed and made, as is required, your reaſons for this your Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56201:6"/>you produce in the particular following Caſes, which we ſhall conſider.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="case">
               <head>Caſe the Firſt.</head>
               <head type="sub">Whether it be Lawful to declare in the words of the Firſt Declaration.</head>
               <p>THe firſt of the Declarations you diſtribute into two parts,<note place="margin">Pa. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> that which concerneth the <hi>Liturgie,</hi> and that which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth the Book of Ordination.</p>
               <p n="2">2. You firſt determine concerning the latter of theſe <hi>viz. The forme and manner of Making, Ordaining, and Conſecrating Biſhops, Preiſts, and Deacons;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pa: <hi>45:</hi>
                  </note> and determine it Lawful thus to declare in this part of the Declaration which you thus enforce: <hi>Moſt that have Livings have ſubſcribed this already, at their Ordination, and read their allowance of it, openly to their ſeveral Congregations upon their Induction, beſides had not this been required in the Act, who knows not that no Conformity without ſubſcribing and reading the nine and thirty Articles could legally ſuffice.</hi> To this Sir, we ſay:</p>
               <p n="3">3. Our queſtion is not what could <hi>legally ſuffice,</hi> but what may be <hi>Conſcientiouſly</hi> done; for this muſt not be violated unto the ſatisfaction of that.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Your Argument, is an Argument of fact, which if ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted true, will not conclude your Reſolution; for you well know a <hi>facto ad jus</hi> will not follow, moſt have done it, therefore all may lawfully do it, is Logick; which the fear of God favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not. Yet Sir:</p>
               <p n="5">5. We preſume to gainſay your confident Aſſertion, <hi>That the moſt who had Livings, had at the writing your book, ſubſcribed the forme and manner of Making, Ordaining, and Conſecrating Biſhops, Preiſts, and Deacons, required by this Act,</hi> cannot but conceive ſtrangely of it; we do not know the moſt who then had Livings, and therefore cannot ask them the queſtion; but we think they muſt be moſt of them <hi>Reordained</hi> according to the new Forme, Presbyterial Ordination had ſure been very Active, and Exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56201:7"/>and Presbyters were eaſie Wheelers, who had well learned <hi>Tempora mu tantur &amp; nos mutamur ab illis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Sir, give us leave to tell you, we had good Livings until the <hi>24th.</hi> of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1662. and yet we were not of the Number of thoſe who ſubſcribed this Book, <hi>Forme and manner at our Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination,</hi> and we believe moſt who were then in Livings, and Epiſcopally Ordained, were in the ſame common Capacity with us, and ſubſcribed the Book which we ſubſcribed, and ſure this Book was not then born, if conceived in our Biſhops brain, it was not brought into the World many days before this Book of yours which giveth it ſuck.</p>
               <p n="7">7. We muſt indeed confeſs we have been informed that the moſt of the Miniſters in <hi>Cheſhire</hi> (and it may be ſome other Dioceſs) in zeale or love to their Livings (more manifeſt then Conſcience or diſcretion) did by a Monſtrous implicite faith ſubſcribe this Book before the <hi>24th</hi> of <hi>Auguſt.</hi> Theſe may evince ſomething of your Argument a <hi>facto,</hi> and yet we muſt tell you they were not all then Ordained, and if this will conclude <hi>ad jus,</hi> we muſt tell you theſe men did at the ſame time, ſubſcribe the Book of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer, and both theſe Declarations, and all this they did in obedience to the Act for Uniformity before their eyes ſaw either of theſe Books; <hi>Ergo</hi> all may lawfully ſo do.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Moreover, Sir, we muſt preſume to acquaint you that we know the Reading ſo many of thirty nine Articles, <hi>Which contain only the Doctrine of Faith, or of the Sacraments,</hi> with an omiſſion of that which concerned the <hi>book of Conſecration</hi> would Legally ſuffice, we are confident you will make no more of this forme and manner of <hi>Making, Ordaining, and Conſecrating Biſhops, Preiſts, and Deacons,</hi> ſave a <hi>Political</hi> though <hi>Eccleſiaſtical order,</hi> and that neither Doctrine of Faith nor Sacraments, and an Aſſent to ſuch Articles as contain <hi>Thoſe,</hi> and <hi>Only</hi> thoſe is required by the Law; The Statute which dictateth Legal ſufficiency.</p>
               <p n="9">9. We expect, Sir, you ſhould reply to us, that the <hi>Book of Conſecration Eſtabliſhed by King</hi> Edward <hi>the Sixth and enforced by Queen</hi> Elizabeth, is much what the ſame with this, and therefore in ſubſcribing that, we have ſubſcribed this.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Good Sir, excuſe us, <hi>ſinaile nonest idem,</hi> there are in this book ſome Additions, and alterations which were not in that,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:56201:7"/>and this may barr our ſubſcription to this; Moreover, Sir, the forme of ſubſcription required by this Law, is ſuch as was never required before by any law, nor given by us to any form or man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Ordination and Conſecration. This requiring our <hi>unfeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Aſſent and conſent</hi> which we unfeignedly profeſs we cannot give.</p>
               <p n="11">11. But, Sir, You have hit the white in your conjecture, that the <hi>firſt part of this Declaration is that which ſticketh with us,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pa. <hi>5:</hi>
                  </note> (viz.) <hi>that which concerneth the Book of Common Prayer,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sect <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and is thus expreſſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I. A. B. <hi>Do declare my unfeigned Aſſent and Conſent to all and everything contained and preſcribed in and by the Book</hi> Entituled, The Book of Common-Prayer, &amp;c. For, Sir, although we could have conformed, we could not,<note place="margin">Pag: <hi>6:</hi>
                  </note> nor (conſidering what you have ſaid) can we yet make and ſubſcribe this Declaration,<note place="margin">Sect <hi>7:</hi>
                  </note> though we are not like Children affrighted with a <hi>long Title,</hi> we are not in judgement ſatisfied to declare concerning the Book what is required.</p>
               <p n="12">12. We Sir, embrace your <hi>Suada,</hi> and <hi>will not ſet an edge on the wordes to wound our ſelves;</hi> yet we muſt ſay, your gloſs doth not ſo much as dull the edge your ſelf hath put upon the words; you tell us the <hi>Object of our Aſſent and Conſent is not the words but things, there are ſeveral expreſſions which though we could ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly read, yet we do not ſo heartily approve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, as we ſeem to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, not every thing as there expreſſed, but every thing contained in the expreſſions muſt have our Aſſent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13. Sir, We muſt be bold to tell you our Controverſie is about <hi>Wordy things,</hi> a Liturgy, a Rubrick, a Forme, of Prayer, and the like: The queſtion is whether theſe be <hi>right words,</hi> to be pronounced? and a <hi>fit form</hi> to be uſed, that in our Miniſtry we may be bound couſe theſe and none other,? and as ſuch Sir, your <hi>things</hi> are <hi>words</hi> and <hi>matters expreſſed,</hi> is the <hi>Mode of expreſſion;</hi> to which, our Conſent and Aſſent muſt be yielded; the Aſſent to a Creed may have the <hi>matter expreſſed</hi> for its object; but Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and Conſent to a Common Prayer Book hath no <hi>adaequate</hi> object but the <hi>Mode, Words, Expreſſions, Forms to be uſed and pronounced;</hi> though Sir, we could Miniſter in and by ſome ſuch Expreſſions, we muſt be well adviſed before we declare <hi>an unfeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:56201:8"/>Aſſent and Conſent</hi> thereunto, The Nonconformaiſts geneally allow the matter of Doctrine, or Petition, in the Common Prayer, <hi>expreſſed and contained,</hi> and have ever quarrelled the Mode, as not a full and fit <hi>wordy Direction</hi> or determination of the miniſtration directed in and by it.</p>
               <p n="14">14. But, Sir, admitting your gloſs; ſome <hi>things contained in ſuch expreſſions,</hi> &amp; ſignified by ſuch <hi>words,</hi> are ſuch to which we cannot <hi>Aſſent</hi> nor <hi>conſent:</hi> For Inſtance, in the Abſolution, a <hi>word</hi> is altered which we conceive hath altered the <hi>thing, (Wherefore we beſeech him to grant us true Repentance,</hi> &amp;c. In the old Book is a formal Prayer) but <hi>(let us Beſeech him in the new book)</hi> ſeemeth to alter it into an authoritative <hi>Sacerdotal abſolution</hi> which we are not convinced to be a ſtanding peice of ſolemn Worſhip in every ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to God, or into a <hi>Miniſterial exhortation</hi> of the people, and then not to ſtick at the impertinent <hi>Amen</hi> of the people, thereto ſubjoyned; we are to be convinced that the words of the Lords Prayer are the neceſſary and only lawful Petition for pardon of ſin in every approach to God, yet that is conſtantly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned.</p>
               <p n="15">15. Again, Sir, <hi>Anſwer,</hi> in the Rubrick is a <hi>word,</hi> but the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of popular reſponds; the Invitation, <hi>Accompany me with an humble voice,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Analepſ. Analepth. <hi>Pa. 58.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and ſay after me,</hi> the <hi>different Characters</hi> in the Petitionary part of the <hi>Letany and Decalogue</hi> are directions for popular Conclamations, all which (be not offended if we tell you in Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> Dialect) is ſo <hi>directly repugnant to the Apoſtles rule; Let all things be done decently and in order; who in the caſe of extraordinary &amp; immediate Elolitions of the ſpirit allowed the people no more, ſave an audible Amen:</hi> That we dare not aſſent nor conſent to things contained in theſe words.</p>
               <p n="16">16, Again, Sir, <hi>Holy</hi> is an adjunct to <hi>Table</hi> frequent in this book, and ſignifieth a <hi>Thing</hi> which we cannot admit; we know no <hi>holineſs</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> places or Inſtruments under the Goſpel, yet will contend that ſuch be handſome: Sir, Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> whom you ſpecially aſſault hath to our knowledge oppoſed the <hi>Prophane neglect, contempt, and abuſe</hi> of the Churches: <hi>Irreverend, unman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly uſage of</hi> the Table, reſerved for the Miniſtration of the Lords Supper, and the <hi>Conſecration of Churches, holineſs of Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> with an equal vigor.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:56201:8"/>
               <p n="17">17. Again, Sir, The <hi>corrupt Tranſlation of the Pſalter, or Pſalmes of</hi> David, <hi>pointed</hi> (unto manifeſt non-ſence) <hi>to be ſung or ſaid in Churches,</hi> varying the <hi>Text from the Original,</hi> yea from the truth it ſelf, <hi>rendring it contrary</hi> thereunto in thoſe ſeveral particulars excepted againſt by the Non-conformiſts, whoſe loud and long clamour, would have engaged the correction of errors, ſo groſs, and obvious, yet even theſe things are retained and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, as things <hi>contained in and preſcribed by this Common Prayer, book,</hi> and to which we muſt declare our unfeigned aſſent and conſent: To this, Sir, we may and muſt add the <hi>corrupt Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the fourth Commandement,</hi> (wherefore the Lord bleſſed the ſeventh day, and hallowed it) contrary to the Original Text, the Bible Tranſlation, and the prudent correction thereof, made in the book prepared for and ſent into <hi>Scotland,</hi> by our late Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates: Though, Sir, we could ſubmiſſively beare theſe things, our Reformation not being at the firſt perfect; yet before we declare our unfeigned aſſent and conſent to ſuch <hi>words,</hi> ſpeaking <hi>things</hi> ſo falſely, we muſt have a better Argument then this (you are not <hi>concerned in the Expreſſions</hi>) which expreſſions are manifeſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, and ſignifications wilfully retayned, and ſeverely impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed after and againſt undeniable exceptions and earneſt Petitions for Reformation.</p>
               <p n="18">18. Give us leave to add one more <hi>(viz.)</hi> thoſe words in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme; <hi>It is certain by Gods word that Children being Baptized dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before they commit actual ſin, are undoubtedly ſaved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="19">19. Sir, it is true, theſe are but <hi>words,</hi> and <hi>an expreſſion,</hi> but theſe words contain in them a <hi>Poſition and Doctrine</hi> aſſerted with the certainty of an Article of Faith, to which we cannot conſent: we can Chriſtianly beleive the Regenerating Nature, Uſe, and efficacy of Baptiſme, and charitably hope the ſalvation of ſuch who die ſubjected thereunto, but that the <hi>undoubted ſalvation of all baptized Infants dying before they commit actual ſin is ortain by the Scriptures,</hi> We confeſs we cannot ſee, nor do we beleive, we do beleive Gods Soveraign <hi>Election</hi> and <hi>Reprobation of perſons,</hi> The Scripture doth declare, <hi>God loved</hi> Jacob <hi>and hated</hi> Eſau, <hi>the Children being not yet born,</hi> much leſs Baptized, nor <hi>having done good or evil, that the purpoſe of God might ſtand according to Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on not of works,</hi> that all who paſs under the adminiſtration of a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:56201:9"/>Saving Ordinance are <hi>Undoubtedly ſaved</hi> is not cleare from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but rather the contrary, things that are revealed belong un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, and to our Children.</p>
               <p n="19">19. We cannot but hope you will in a ſecond review of theſe, and the like expreſſions, finde our aſſent and conſent is required to thoſe <hi>Words,</hi> which <hi>Without forming an edge to wound our ſelves, do contain and preſcribe things</hi> to which no rational man in his right minde can declare the ſame.</p>
               <p n="20">20. We now proceed to conſider another Objection which you ſlate and reſolve in this Caſe, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Though we could Uſe the things,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pa. <hi>7.</hi> Objection <hi>2:</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>it is only for peace ſake, and in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to Authority, and not that we would chuſe or can abſolutely approve of theſe things indifferent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this Sir, you tell us we may not approve <hi>Abſolutely</hi> but <hi>Comparatively.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt you ſay in <hi>Charity to our Governours we conceive to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in the Declaration,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag: <hi>8:</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>becauſe it is impoſſible, all men ſhould in ſo many perticulars, and various Circumſtances be of one minde:</hi> But Sir.</p>
               <p n="21">21. We humbly conceive we do not break Charity to our Governors, if we conclude that they knowing <hi>all men could not in ſo many perticulars, and various circumſtances be of one minde;</hi> and believing <hi>Unanimity</hi> to be the bond of <hi>Uniformity,</hi> did deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine to knock off from publique Miniſtration in the Church, all who were not of the ſame minde, and who would not Declare the ſame in ſuch words as were by them preſcribed.</p>
               <p n="22">22. Truly Sir, we ſee very little cauſe to believe the Act will allow ſuch a <hi>Comparitive approbation of the Common Prayer book</hi> as you do expiers. It might ſomthing ſatisfy us, if we had our aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance from our Legiſlators that ſuch a Comparative approbation would ſatisfy the <hi>Law,</hi> but they are herein ſilent, and the Law giveth not ſufficient Reaſon on which we may conclude it.</p>
               <p n="23">23. You ſay the <hi>Grounds of this Aſſent and conſent are not ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in in the Act,</hi> if by the <hi>Grounds</hi> you mean the <hi>Reaſons inducing the Legiſlators to require ſuch an aſſent and conſent;</hi> we muſt be bold to deny what you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ff m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nd intreate you to let us know what you make there words in the Act; <hi>Now in regard that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:56201:9"/>conduceth to the ſetling to peace in this Nation (which is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired by all good men,) not to the honour of our Religion, and the propagation thereof, then an Univerſal agreement in the publick wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of Almighty God, and to the end Uniformity may be effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it is enacted &amp;c.</hi> Sir, we know not how to underſtand an <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Law,</hi> if <hi>Univerſal Agreement,</hi> and <hi>Uniformity</hi> to be effected, be not declared Grounds for enjoying ſuch a Declaration of Aſſent, and Conſent.</p>
               <p n="24">24. Such a <hi>Comparitive Aſſent and Conſent,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pa. 9:10</note> as you aſſert will not well paſs as <hi>unfeigned,</hi> avoiding a <hi>ſevere Penalty</hi> ſecuring <hi>a good Living, and a Legal opportunity of ſerving the Church, not ſhewing our ſelves croſs to Authority, and delivering our Family from ruine,</hi> are bad enducements to an <hi>unfeigned Aſſent and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> all men will underſtand them Temptations to a <hi>Faint un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned Aſſent and Conſent,</hi> let what will be required, if this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon may bear weight, it ſhall not paſs without an unfeigned Aſſent and Conſent.</p>
               <p n="25">25. Sir, we ſee with little cauſe you have to quarrel,<note place="margin">Pa. 10.</note> that it is reported the Aſſent and Conſent declared muſt be <hi>Free;</hi> For Sir, this <hi>Freedome</hi> is neceſſary and Eſſential to <hi>unfeigned:</hi> An Act <hi>Extorted</hi> will never be judged <hi>unfeigned,</hi> but ſuſpected of Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie; if any report it to be expreſſed in the Declaration, let them beare their blame, but truely we think it is unavoidably implyed.</p>
               <p n="26">26. Sir, <hi>To remove all ſcruples from us for ever,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pa. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>you offer us the Act for the interpretation of it ſelf,</hi> It would to ſome of us be worth ſome hundreds by the year, if you could lend us your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding alſo; we grant to you that <hi>the words, immediately forgoing the Declaration are theſe; Every Miniſter ſhall declare his unfeigned Aſſent and Conſent, to the uſe of all things in the ſaid book contained and preſcribed in theſe words and none other;</hi> But what then.</p>
               <p n="27">27. We agree with you, we muſt declare our unfeigned Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and Conſent but to what? <hi>To all things with reſpect to their uſe, and that in theſe words, and no other;</hi> But Sir, that this refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth our Aſſent and Conſent to the <hi>uſing Act,</hi> and <hi>That only</hi> we cannot ſee, theſe Acts have for their Object, <hi>All things contained &amp; preſcribed in and by the Book of Common Prayer, &amp;c.</hi> And the <hi>uſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:56201:10"/>thereof</hi> is the <hi>End</hi> of this Aſſent and Conſent, ſo that the Act puts this plain Interpretation on the required Declaration, <hi>Every Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſhall Uniformely uſe the book, but unanimity being the ſpur and bond of Uniformity, they ſhall declare an Unfeigned Aſſent and Conſent to all things contained and preſcribed in and by the book;</hi> So that we muſt <hi>Uſe</hi> the Book with a <hi>Minde</hi> perſwaded of the <hi>Truth and Goodneſs of the things to be uſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="28">28. This Senſe of the Law we are induced to receive be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. This Declaration <hi>Reſpecteth the uſe of the Comomon Prayer,</hi> and is the <hi>Security of Unfeignedneſs in that Act;</hi> the uſe of it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a <hi>Minde fully Aſſenting</hi> to the things contained, and <hi>Freely conſenting</hi> to the things preſcribed in and by this Book, would be but formal, forced, and feigned; we are confident our Legiſlators intended to obviate all haltings in Conformity, and this is only done by requiring an unfeigned <hi>Aſſent and Conſent to the uſe;</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an unfeigned <hi>Aſſent and conſent, to all and every thing therein contained and preſcribed.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. The <hi>Uſe of the book</hi> is not once mentioned in the Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as the Object of the <hi>Aſſent and conſent,</hi> but the <hi>Things therein contained and preſcribed</hi> are ever expreſſed in the Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the <hi>Uſe of it</hi> is expteſſed in the Law, only as the <hi>End</hi> ſecured by the Declaration.</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Univerſal agreement in the publick Worſhip of Almighty God,</hi> is declared to be the ground of this Law, and <hi>Uniformity is the end</hi> thereof, both which can be only effected by the <hi>unanimity</hi> of the Adminiſtrators, in the things to be by them uniformely uſed.</item>
                  <item>4. The uſing Act is provided for, promiſed, and ſecured by the next following Declaration in theſe tearms, (<hi>I do declare that I will Conforme to the Liturgie of the Church of</hi> England <hi>as it is now Eſtabliſhed by Law,</hi>) Conforme; what is that to a Miniſter? But that I will <hi>Uſe it,</hi> and the <hi>the things contained and preſcribed in and by it:</hi> This is Sir, your own ſenſe of <hi>Conformity;</hi> and ſure Sir, you will not ſay this ſecond Declaration doth <hi>Actum agere</hi> do over what was done in the firſt Declaration, theſe two muſt differ each from other; That Declareth Aſſent and Conſent to the <hi>Matter and Things.</hi> This to the Act <hi>and Uſe thereof;</hi> Sir, until your ſenſe of the Declaration be cleared from theſe excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:56201:10"/>or declared by the Legiſlators, give us leave to tell you <hi>We could do ſome things directed in the Rubrick, but cannot Aſſent or Conſent to the direction.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>We could at the Communion <hi>commend the poor to the Charity of the people,</hi> but we underſtand not their other <hi>Devotions</hi> to be then gathered, the affected title <hi>Offertorie</hi> maketh it look like ſomething exploded at our firſt Reformation from Popery.</p>
               <p>We could <hi>receive the Collection from the Deacons or Church-Wardens and place it on the Table,</hi> but we underſtand not the <hi>hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble preſenting and placing it on the holy Table,</hi> it hereby ſoundeth like a <hi>Sacrifice;</hi> we could <hi>Eate and Drink the remaines of Bread, and Wine with ſome of the Communicants,</hi> but we know no diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (Communion ended) between <hi>Conſecrated</hi> and <hi>unconſecrated Elements,</hi> nor ſee we on what ground to Conſent and Aſſent that the one be <hi>Eaten at the Holy Table by the Preiſt and Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants,</hi> and the other <hi>Taken home to the Curates Houſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We could hanſomely cover the Bread with a Napkin, but we underſtand not what is meant by <hi>Reverent placing them on the Holy Table, and covering them with a Linnen Cloath,</hi> nor can we Aſſent or Conſent thereunto.</p>
               <p n="29">29. Reverend Sir, Our Fathers were, and our ſelves might be content in ſome things to Symbolize with <hi>Rome,</hi> when our face was from hers, but we cannot unfeignedly Aſſent and Conſent unto ſuch Simbolizing with her; Now moſt men think, and Nonconformiſts boldly affirme our face is towards her, yet we pray for the peace and Glory of <hi>Englands</hi> Church, that the Goſpel may in her Flouriſh in Power and Purity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="case">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:56201:11"/>
               <head>Caſe II.</head>
               <head type="sub">VVhether it be lawful declare in the words of the ſecond De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration.<note place="margin">Caſe. 2th. Pa. <hi>13:14</hi>
                  </note>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. SIr, we muſt tell you, <hi>The many words in this Declaration affright us not,</hi> yet we cannot but be affected to obſerve the perſons who quarreled at the Covenant, to impoſe an Oath, or Declaration Tantamount, ſo full of words, <hi>Turpe eſt Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctori.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. But we conſent to attend your motion in taking this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration in peices, and you diſtribute it into three parts, that which concerns the <hi>Taking Armes againſt the King, Conformity,</hi> and the <hi>Oath, called the Solemne League and Covenant,</hi> in each of which we ſhall conſider your reſolution and Reaſons; The firſt part you divide into theſe two Caſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="cases">
               <head>Caſe III. <hi>1.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Caſe <hi>3.</hi> Pa. <hi>15:</hi>
                  </note> Whether it be lawful for us to delare that it is not lawful upon any pretence whatſoever, to take Armes againſt the King.</head>
               <head>Caſe IV.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>2.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Caſe</hi> 4. <hi>Pa.</hi> 16.17.</note> Whether it be lawful to declare that we abhor that Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous Poſition of taking Armes by the Kings Authority, againſt his Perſon, or thoſe that are Commiſſioned by him.</head>
               <p n="1">1. SIr, Theſe two you conclude in the Affirmative on ſo ſharp promiſes that none dare, or in prudence can ſpeak the Negative, or withſtand you; <hi>Tower</hi> and <hi>Tyburne</hi> are terrible places.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This part of the Declaration doth not much concern us;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:56201:11"/>out oppoſition to the late Rebellion againſt the King, our reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Armes taken againſt him; our conſtancy of Loyalty under the Croſs; do Iondly witneſs you and we cannot be in this particular at any great diſtance; yet we know ſome Loyal hearts who ſtumble, for whoſe ſake we wiſh you had more thoroughly argued thoſe Caſes by ſome <hi>Medium</hi> which they might venture to meet you at, we will tell you what we have heard whiſpered by men of Loyal hearts.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Some ſay this Declaration is the <hi>perſonal affection of a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent private opinion,</hi> which being changeable can give no ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ſo reacheth not the end for which it is exacted; theſe men in zeal to his Majeſty could paſs a <hi>Promiſſory Oath</hi> that they <hi>would not take Armes againſt the King,</hi> for they conceive their Act is fully within their power, though the ſtronger reaſons they may meet with in men or books, may alter their preſent opinions though declared under the moſt ſacred Oath.</p>
               <p n="4">4, Some ſay this Declaration is <hi>Dogmatical;</hi> by perſons whoſe Opinion cannot end the Political ſtrife which hath been, and is in the World about it, and ſo it cannot reach the end of ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Declaration. Theſe ſtumble that the tearms are ſo indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite as to render the Poſition applycable to every Kingdome.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Some ſay the tearms are <hi>dubious</hi> if not falſe, it being inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely inſerted, <hi>It is not lawful to take Armes againſt the King, on any pretence what ſoever;</hi> Theſe think though this may be true, and ſquare to the Lawes of <hi>this Kingdome,</hi> the conſtitution of other Kingdomes may make it contrary, and although <hi>our King is,</hi> and we hope ever will be ſo qualified that in reference to him it may be true; yet it is not impoſſible for a King <hi>Regis perſonam exuere,</hi> in a natural or moral madneſs, or Phrenſie, to turn Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, yea Beaſt, waving his Royal Place, violently extrajudicially, extramagiſterially to aſſault his Subject, as <hi>Saul</hi> did <hi>David:</hi> In this caſe men think Nature doth dictate it, and Scripture doth juſtifie a man, <hi>Se defendendo vim vi repellere,</hi> to take Armes, though by rallying the men of <hi>Belial<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> not to <hi>reſiſt</hi> yet to <hi>restrain</hi> the King, and thoſe who are Commiſſioned by him, until they make good their retreat, and more ſafely run out of his reach: And this Sir, is ſome pretence, on which to ſpeak of the <hi>Law of Nature,</hi> is not as you affirme a <hi>Subterfuge,</hi> and in anſwer to your
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56201:12"/>
                  <hi>what ſaith the Scripture?</hi> they ſay it ſeemeth to be their <hi>Sheild,</hi> this pretence being ſquare to and conſiſtent with profeſſed obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
               <p n="6">6 To ſome it ſoundeth harſh to declare it a <hi>trayterous Poſitian to take Arms by the Kings authority againſt the Kings perſon or thoſe Commiſſioned by him,</hi> theſe will not be perſwaded that if Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> had by vertue of the broad Seal, (brought to her in Sanctuary by the then Arch-Biſhop of <hi>York</hi>) arrayed and armed men againſt <hi>Richard Duke of Gloceſter,</hi> poſſeſſing the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of King <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>5th.</hi> ſhe had thereby become a Traytor, theſe men think it not impoſſible for <hi>England</hi> again to ſee a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidious Protector of the perſon of an Infant-King, and tremble to think that this Declaration may become the <hi>baſis of Treaſon,</hi> and <hi>Guard of Rebellion,</hi> if ſome Ruſſians ſhould (which God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend) ſeize the perſon of a King, he is a man from whom Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions may be by fear extorted, whereby true Loyalty muſt be on their ſide, and Treaſon on the part of the Kings Counſel, Kindred &amp; Miniſters of State, if Arming againſt his Perſon, by his Authority though on ſuch a pretence, <hi>quo poſito abſurdum ſequens non eſt ponendum;</hi> But Sir, theſe are a <hi>Noli me tangere</hi> which we ſhall not defend.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="case">
               <head>Caſe V.</head>
               <head type="sub">Whether it be Lawful to declare that we will Conforme,<note place="margin">Caſe 5th.. Pa. <hi>19:20</hi>
                  </note> to the Litturgie of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as it is now by Law Eſtabliſhed.</head>
               <p>THis Sir, is the ſecond part of the Declaration to which you have ſaid little, and we ſhall ſay leſs, only mind you that this declaring <hi>Our Aſſent and Conſent to the uſe of the Liturgie;</hi> the foregoing Declaration doth determine <hi>Our unfeigned Aſſent and conſent to the Things and Matters to be uſed;</hi> that <hi>unanimity,</hi> is the ſpring and ſpurr, ground and guard of this promiſed Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But Sir, we haſten after you to the Conſideration of the third part of this Declaration, which concerneth the Solemn
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:56201:12"/>League and Covenant, which is, indeed, the <hi>Great Mountaine in our way,</hi> to be removed by a faith of Miracles; This you do again divide into three parts, its Obligation, its unlawfulneſs in its ſelf, and its Oppoſition to the Laws and Liberties of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but your Reſolution is to the particular Caſes follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="case">
               <head>Caſe VI.</head>
               <head type="sub">Whether we may lawfully declare in theſe words,<note place="margin">Caſe 6th. Pa. <hi>221:23.</hi>
                  </note> I do bold theſe lies no Obligation on me nor any other perſon from the Oath commonly called the Solemn League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, to endeavour any Alteration of Government either in Church or State.</head>
               <p n="1">1 TO this, Sir, you tell us it is <hi>No great venture to ſay ſuch who have taken the Covenant may thus declare,</hi> This we confeſs is <hi>facile dictum,</hi> but the <hi>quod demonſtrandum reſtat,</hi> the convinceing demonſtration of this hath made many learned men ſweat, and appeareth, <hi>Hic labor, hoc opus,</hi> a knot cut by the ſword of Authority, whilſt it cannot be looſed by Religious Reaſon.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We conſent to your conceſſions to the conteſtors for the Covenant <hi>(viz.) That the Covenant illegally taken and given may bind: Secondly,</hi> That <hi>it binds not to alteration of the Government of State: Thirdly, That the unlawful matter made it void,</hi> ipſo facto: <hi>Fourthly,</hi> That Mr. <hi>Crofton, and the Covenanters-plea do grant that the unlawful matter dath void the Covenant ipſo facto.</hi> But now Sir, give us leave to call for your ſtrong Reaſons.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Here Sir, you pitch, and your work is to prove that the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant ſo far as it engageth the Takers of it againſt Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Exſtirpation, or change of it is unlawful, and ſinful in the matter of it;</hi> This made good <hi>Nobis eris magnus Apollo:</hi> We ſhall therefore with all dilligence obſerve your motion in maintenance hereof.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Your firſt onſet is by Dr. <hi>Saunderſons</hi> diſtinction of <hi>Iuramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum illicitum de ſe, &amp; per accidens,</hi> and you grant the matter of the Covenant, is not <hi>ſimply and of it ſelf unlawful;</hi> your Antago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:56201:13"/>lye ſtrongly entrenched in this, and thence defend the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant againſt all other aſſaults, it had been a noble Enterpriſe to have beaten them at this weapon; but <hi>ad impoſſibile nemo tenea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur:</hi> We joyn iſſues with you on the ſecond, and wiſh we may ſee you may prove the Covenant <hi>Ratione ſubjecti</hi> by the accident of its <hi>Takers condition and Capacity</hi> is unlawful in the matter of it; Yet Sir,</p>
               <p n="5">5. We muſt make bold to minde you that the learned Caſuiſt (on whom you depend in this Caſe and Determination) hath determined with an <hi>Ordinary,</hi> his words are <hi>Hac Iurament a ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie non obligant, or dinarié dico quia fortaſſe poſſunt dare Caſus in quibus Iuramentum quod videtur alicui legi communitatis aut vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cationis adverſari, &amp; ſi non debuerit ſuſſepi ſuſeptum tamen poteſt obligari;</hi> Sir, we ſtudy looſing, not binding in this great Caſe, yet cannot but ſay on all ſides the Covenant is confeſſed to be an <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Oath,</hi> and it is a queſtion whether it can be brought within your Caſuiſts <hi>Ordinarie,</hi> the advocates of the Covenant think it no hard taske to bring the Covenant into your Caſuiſts <hi>Exception,</hi> and ſo conclude <hi>Suſcepi non debuerit ſuſceptum tamen obligat,</hi> we leave it to them if they dare to make it good, our work is to weigh what you ſay to the contrary.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Addreſſing your ſelf to your proof you have moſt prudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly waved the <hi>Ius divinum</hi> of your Church Government, which to affirme <hi>Non multum ab inſania differt;</hi> you conſider the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanters as <hi>ſingle Perſons,</hi> or as <hi>vinted in the great body of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> Now Sir, your field fills us with a reviving murmer, of of which alas we muſt ſit down and ſing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Expectata ſeges vanis illuſit arenis.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="case">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:56201:13"/>
               <head>Caſe VII.</head>
               <head type="sub">Whether any private or ſingle perſon can lawfully endeavour the alteration of Church Government by vertue of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.<note place="margin">Caſe <hi>7.</hi> a. <hi>26</hi>
                  </note>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. SIR, <hi>This</hi> (you ſay) <hi>ſeemeth much to be the proper Caſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Parliament which impoſed the Covenant are diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and become private perſons,</hi> But Sir</p>
               <p n="2">2. Do you not here build on a <hi>Petio principii?</hi> That the long Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament is <hi>not diſſolved,</hi> we dare not ſay; but it hath been ſaid: and thoſe words in the Statute which concerneth their continuance, <hi>whatſoever ſhall happen or be done to the diſſolving them ſhall be void and null,</hi> are a ſtone at which our Conſciences cannot but ſtumble whilſt we are in obedience to preſent Laws ſubmiſſively ſilent.</p>
               <p n="3">3. You conclude the Covenant to be onely <hi>private</hi> and <hi>perſonal</hi> an obligation on <hi>ſingle perſons:</hi> but Sir, Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> hath affirmed,<note place="margin">An <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alepſis Sect <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> it is <hi>publick</hi> and <hi>National, Iuramentum reale</hi> obliging <hi>all the Nation,</hi> and all <hi>after-Generations, fide Anglorum</hi> thereby engaged. This he hath demonſtrated beyond our capacity of contradiction and enforced by the conſentient judgement of 600. Divines moſt of them yet liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. You, Sir, are pleaſed to tell us, you have not uſed one Argument anſwered or prevented by Mr. <hi>Crofton;</hi> yet Sir,<note place="margin">Pa. 13<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> you nor any other have not ſo much as attempted an Anſwer to this Poſition of Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> which ſtands intire and unaſlaul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed.</p>
               <p n="4">4. You ſuppoſe each ſingle perſon who ſwear the Covenant in ſuch a capacity, as to be concludent by your ſubſequent Arguments; The Truth is, our Affections are ſuch, as make us wiſh it were ſo, but to ſatisfie our Conſciences in <hi>abjuring</hi> (you are angry at that word, we will therefore ſay diſclaiming,) <hi>the Obligation</hi> of the Coverant, we muſt have our Jadgements convinced it is ſo, becauſe our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration doth diſcleim the Obligation of the Covenant on our ſelves <hi>or any other perſon;</hi> which cannot be done if we conceive any perſon to have taken it who is not in the ſame common capacity with our ſelves.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Upon theſe ungranted Principles you conclude, for ſuch to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:56201:14"/>ſtand ingaged by a publick Covenant againſt a ſetled Government, to <hi>endeavour the exſtirpation or change of it,</hi> is palpably ſinful; both as ſuch a Covenant, and ſuch endeavours are againſt the Right of the King; the Lawes of the Land, the priviledges of Parliament, Liberties of the Subject; and former obligations laid on the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, all Arguments of weight; but ſo ſick of a <hi>Noli me tangere,</hi> that they ſound in our ears, a <hi>Ne plus ultra.</hi> Edge-tools which make your Antagoniſts cry <hi>Tolle legem, &amp; fiat diſputatio</hi> Who dare touch at them, did not your ſencures of us as <hi>Fures, Felones, proditores de ſe</hi> cut our conſciences and conſtrain our conſideration and utmoſt endeavours of conviction; we therefore affirming nothing, will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture to weigh your following demonſtration of the ſinful mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Covenant in reference to thoſe particulars.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="cases">
               <head>Caſe VIII. Whether to endeavour to alter the Government of the Church be againſt the Right of the King.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Caſe 8th.</hi> Pa. 28.29.30.</note>
               </head>
               <head>Caſe IX.</head>
               <head type="sub">Whether to endeavour thus against the Right of the King as ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged thereunto by the Covenant,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Caſe 9th.</hi> Pa. 32.33.</note> be ſinful.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THeſe two Caſes contain your firſt Argument to prove the matter of the Covenant ſinful and unlawful. An An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagoniſt would much quarrel at your method, management and terms in his diſcourſe: but we ſeeking ſatisfaction purſue your ſcope, and paſs by ſuch Peccadilloes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Your major Propoſition is determined in your ſecond caſe, <hi>(viz.)</hi> that to endeavour againſt the Right of the King as oblieged thereunto by the Covenant, is ſinful.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In this, Sir, we ſhall not diſſent from you, we find Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> grant it, candidly conceding to the <hi>Oxford</hi> Reaſons, [that no peace can be firm and well grounded which is not bottomed in Juſtice, whoſe proper and adaequate act is <hi>Ius ſuum cuique,</hi> unleſs. the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:56201:14"/>Power and Liberty, of King, Parliament and Subject, be preſerved full and entire; he therefore cryeth out Specifie the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in this Covenant as to theſe particulars, I cannot read or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand if they be not all ſecured by the ſame] Truly Sir we cannot but do the Covenant that right, as to obſerve, <hi>it bindeth its Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,</hi> to preſerve the Authority as well as the Perſon of the King, and we cannot eaſily believe <hi>it bindeth,</hi> in any thing againſt the Kings Right.</p>
               <p n="3">3. We hope, Sir, we may without offence obſerve, the Kings <hi>Right of Prerogative is ill pleaded</hi> by ſuch who themſelves deſpiſe and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regard it, diſobeying the directions of his Royal Declaration, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Eccleſiaſtical affairs dictated by his Supremacy in Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical cauſes; they give cauſe to be ſuſpected to throw it in the way of Antagoniſts as a ſtumbling ſtone on which to break their legs or necks, who uſe it as a ſtepping ſtone in the way of their unwarranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble rigour and ſeverity.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Sir, we are ſo heartily devouted to the ſervice of the King, that we dare not in the leaſt detract from his Royal Prerogitive; we well know <hi>England</hi> hath its Statute <hi>de Prerogativa Regis, as Rome</hi> had her <hi>Lex Regia;</hi> we unfeignedly wiſh this were amplified and made as legible as other Statutes: yet, Sir, the ſevere cenſures paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in Parliament upon Dr. <hi>Manwaring,</hi> and <hi>Sibthorp</hi> do loud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proclaim a poſſibility for Church-men, to ſcrue the Prerogative of the King beyond its due pitch, and the proportion of <hi>Englands</hi> Conſtitution.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Your Major propoſition allowed, we might weigh your proof of the Mino<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>(viz.)</hi> your Eighth Caſe, To <hi>endeavour to alter the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Church,</hi> is againſt the Right of the King.</p>
               <p n="6">6. To the proofe of this you tell us, it is againſt the Right of the King as Executor of the Law: and you aſſign for your firſt Reaſon, Church-Officers are the Kings Commiſſioners, &amp; they taken away the head muſt fall; Good Sir give us a cleare Anſwer to theſe two Enquiries.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Are Eccleſiaſtical Officers eſſential to the Regality of the King; <hi>No Biſhop no King</hi> hath been an <hi>Eventnal,</hi> but is it a <hi>Moral</hi> truth? Were there no Kings where there was no Biſhops? Were not Kings in Nations, when all Church Government was in the <hi>Pope,</hi> and his Subſtitutes? Supremacy in Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical may
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:56201:15"/>add to the glory but not the being of the King; <hi>Eraſtus</hi> himſe would not ſay Kings ceaſe to be King; if they minde, meddle not with, Church-affaires; we are not-yet perſwaded that a Royal head muſt needs ſtand on Religious Shoulders, and fall when theſe are withdrawn.</item>
                  <item>2. Are theſe ſpecifical Commiſſioners eſſential to the Kings Regality, that, Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops &amp;c. taken away, this Head muſt fall? May not National, Privincial, and Claſſical Presbyteries become the Kings Commiſſioners in the ſlead of Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, Deans, Commiſſaries, Chancellors, &amp;c? May not the Kings Supremacy exſiſt in, and be executed over, and by them, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtuted thereunto?</item>
               </list>
               <p n="7">7. Your firſt <hi>Medium</hi> ſeemeth to be of little force to prove. To en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour after Church Government, is againſt the Kings Right as Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutor of the Law: your next is more general <hi>(viz.)</hi> Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to endeavour to e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>pate the Government of the Church, doth direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oppoſe the whole comſe of our lives againſt the Kings Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and that, lay you, is the ſenſe of the Covenanters themſelves.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Sir, If you had ſaid, To endeavour to exſtitpate, doth oppoſe us ni to this Government the whole courſe of our affections, you had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſpoken the Covenanters ſenſe; yet they will not ſlick to extend it to the whole courſe of our lives, under thoſe limitations, Acts law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, <hi>In our places and Callings, through the grace of God.</hi> But, Sir, they will tell you, Theſe are Acts of endeavour for exſtirpation, other then what you mention: ſuch are theological diſputation, ſubmiſs ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, popular Groans, or Complaints of greivances by and under it, which are conſiſtent with ſubmiſſion to it whilſt exiſtent, thus it may be in all Corperations, and the Church is not excepted.</p>
               <p n="9">9. But, Sir, ſome do and will deny this Government to be the Kings Government, Eſtabliſhed and animated by the Laws whereof it is his Right to be Executor: this you attempt to prove, and in its time and place we ſhall conſider; At preſent let it be obſerved, this Government was not at firſt animated by the Kings authority, Acted not in the Kings name, but challenged ſomtimes a forinſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, but ever a Divine intrinſecal power, for its principle diſtinct from, yea oppoſite to the Kings Authority: its ſubjects were with much difficulty, and the pinch of <hi>Premunire</hi> brought to the ſubmis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Clergie, after which the Kings Laws have indeed limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:56201:15"/>reſtrained, regulated, directed, and in ſome things authorized' theſe Governours, who yet Acting in their name, and under their own Seds, and affirming themſelves to be the upholding Eſſential animation to Regality, by their Cry <hi>No Biſhops no King;</hi> make Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanters conceive, they yet think ſcorn to o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> this Government as animated by the King and his Laws, though they object it as a ſtone, on which they wiſh to ſee their Oppoſers run their heads un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til they daſh out their brains.</p>
               <p n="10">10. You further urge <hi>To endeavour the alteration of Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is againſt the Right of the King as Legiſlator;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pa. <hi>30.</hi>
                  </note> the Covenant binding to do, without the Kings conſent, &amp; whether he would or no.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Sir, to this we muſt tell you, we do not finde in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant any ſuch words as that we ſhall endeavour to exſtirpate or alter the Government without the Kings conſent; not do we finde in it any words which by a fair and genuine conſtruction can bear any ſuch ſenſe, and we finde the Covenanters do deny it: Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> whom you moſt aſſault doth own the King as chief,<note place="margin">Ana lepſ. Ana lepth. Pa. <hi>98.99</hi>
                  </note> though not ſole Legiſlator, and allots Acts of endeavour to procure the Kings conſent, to which the Covenant, he ſaith, doth oblige.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Truly that limitation on the Covenant is ſo juſt, ful, and legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>(viz.) Through the grace of God in our places and Callings,</hi> that we cannot but yeild to Mr. <hi>Crofton;</hi> the defence of the Kings power, is not repugnant to the dutys of our particular Callings, and Capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. I hope, a Miniſter may by his preaching,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id</hi> pa 7.6.6</note> or a Divine by Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation in the Schools endeavour the Correction, Reformation and Exſtirpation, of any Error, Hereſie, Schiſm or Superſtition, and yet not intrench on his Majeſties Jurisdiction, yea, in reference to a judicial Correction, Reformation and Exſtirpation, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be done without the Kings conſent, mens endeavour may be in their places and Callings by Counſel, Propoſals, Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance, Petition and Supplication to procure his Majeſties conſent, and Authority: Sir, this limitation is ſo clear, and comprehenſive that we think, <hi>if the King pleaſe,</hi> is ſo fully conditioned in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, that it muſt be procured to effect the exſtirpation Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, only the Covenanters ſtand obliged to a conſtant endeavour to perſwade and procure the ſame.</p>
               <p n="13">13. The condition in which the King was when the Covenant was made, we cannot commend, we can not but lament
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:56201:16"/>and condemn. Yet Sir, to do all men right, [the Meſſages, Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrances, and Petitions of the two Houſes of Parliament, the confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence at the Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi> the Votes upon the Kings Coceſſions, (though but to ſuppoſed Epiſcopacy for three years, the violence to which themſelves were expoſed] do loudly witneſs all faithful Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venaters did conceive themſelves bound to procure the Kings con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, not to exſtirpare this Government, as you ſay whether the King would or no.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Now admitting what you ſay to be true, the Government of the Church is under the King, the alteration thereof did concern his power, &amp; the King gave not conſent unto the Covenant, yet you finde ſomething doth intercept your concluſion; For Sir, there are Acts of endeavour for Alteration and Exſtirpation, which are law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful proper to Subjects, and conſiſient with the Kings Executive, and Legiſlative Right and power, yea unto the perſwading and procuring his Conſent and Concurrence to and with the ſame.</p>
               <p n="14">14. You Sir affirme the King did not conſent unto the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant but did Proclaime his diſſent.</p>
               <p n="15">15. The Proclamation againſt the Covenant hath been often urged, and by the advocates for the Covenant admitted, yet it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth upon us a doubt, whether there ever were any ſuch Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation; we do not conclude it, but ſhall give you the grounds of Conjecture: (1.) We never ſaw it, nor Copy of it, (2.) The Anticovenaters, neither <hi>Oxford</hi> Reaſons, Doctor <hi>Langbain,</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Gauden</hi> who laid much ſtreſs upon it, have ever produced it, or tranſcribed its Copy; Doctor <hi>Featly</hi> his Ghou (as Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> calleth it) gives us by miſtake the Proclamation againſt the Vow and Covenant, inſtead of the Proclamation againſt the Solemne Leage and Covenant: (3.) His Majeſty in his Meditations on the Covenant maketh no mention of ſuch Proclamation, and only aggravateth the ſame as impoſed without his conſent, not againſt his Interdict.</p>
               <p n="16">16. Sir, be pleaſed to help us to a copy of this Proclamation and inform us where to finde the Original, for until it be produced the Anticovenanters have no ground on which to ſtand, nor can the Obligation be (without it) voided; your Probleme whether the Kings future conſent could revive it, doth fall, until it appear he did fully formerly void it.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:56201:16"/>
               <p n="17">17. Sir we readily ſubcribe <hi>Ameſius</hi> his rule [<hi>Datur irritio jura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti aliquando per Superiores</hi> but it muſt be <hi>[in illa ipſa materia ſint Superiores circa quam verſatur juramentum]</hi> But ſir Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> hath told us the Effect cannot be produced without the conſent and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of Superiors, but the Act about which the Covenant doth converſe and to which it doth obliege is fully within the power of the inferior or ſubject;<note place="margin">Analepſ. Analeſth. Pa. <hi>121</hi>
                  </note> he urgeth from the Reverend Biſhop of <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coln: [vix quenquam quigaudet uſu rationis, ita plene ſub alterius po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtate eſſe, quia ut fit quantum ad aliqua ſaltem ſui juris]</hi> and it infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, I hope no adult child, on obſervation of the irregularities in the Government of a Family ſhall be barred from vowing in his place and calling, to his power and capacity, to reform the ſame; exſtirpation is a parental Act, but the child may endeavour, and he doth conclude of this Covenant <hi>[Obligat hoc genus juramenti non ad effectum ſed conatum]</hi> Again Sir, <hi>The Superior muſt in the day he heareth of it renuendo renuere, tollendo tollere;</hi> you muſt let us ſee the Proclamation before we can conclude our Superior did thus void this Oath.</p>
               <p n="18">18. Sir, your Proclamation allowed, you are of Divines the firſt, who hath made it a Probleme, Whether the Kings after conſent could revive the voided Oath, <hi>Secundae cogitationes ſunt meliores,</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents may, on ſecond thoughts, allow what in paſſion they may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne, their condemnation is not fatal, and irrecvocable. The ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiſt Prelate hath determined Impoſſibility ariſing from the right of another may be removed by after conſent;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> Sauu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſon.</note> and this once remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Oath binds; It is not clear the late King did void this oath, but it is clear he did declare <hi>Good men ſhould beſt pleaſe God and me by keeping the Covenant.</hi> And as things now ſtand doth witneſs this Declaration to be the reſult of ſerious and ſecond thoughts.</p>
               <p n="19">19. You Sir, in cloſe of your Argument, tell us <hi>The ſword cut off the hard bargain for ſuſpenſion of Epiſcopacy for three years, and the objection with it;</hi> Let us make bold to tell you,<note place="margin">Pa. <hi>36.</hi>
                  </note> the ſame ſword brought out ſucceding Superiour under a more and expreſs aſſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Oath, and mandate to all his ſubjects to advance it: Sir it is a Probleme which we cannot reſolve; Whether political parents be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing changeable, <hi>(One Generation paſſeth and another cometh)</hi> he who ſuceeding exiſteth our preſent Parent do not by his mandate ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige us to the Oath diſallowed by his Predeceſſor, whoſe interdict
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:56201:17"/>dyed with him. Sir, we offer this to be conſidered; we do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude it: for ſo to do who ſeeth not it is neither ſafe nor prudent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="case">
               <head>
                  <hi>Caſe X.</hi> Whether the covenanting to endeavour the exſtirpation of Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal Government,<note place="margin">Caſe 10th. pa. <hi>37.</hi>
                  </note> be againſt the Lanes, and conſequently ſinful.</head>
               <p n="1">1. YOur reſolution to this Caſe is moſt-what a recapiculation of your former Argument obnoxious to much exception, but we reſolve not to ſtumble at termes and expreſſions, but to weigh the ſtrength of Reaſon, ſeeking ſatisfaction to our conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that if poſſible we might again recover our Livings, this (we note) urgeth your ſecond Argument, to prove the matter of the Covenant unlawful becauſe againſt the Laws.</p>
               <p n="2">2. You obſerve, Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> and <hi>the Covenanter plea</hi> deny Epiſcopal Government to be Eſtabliſhed by Law, which, ſay you, to prove, is a taske impoſſible. That is true, for they cannot prove a Negative, if you make good the contrary you do the work as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for you, as <hi>Negation</hi> is proper to them, <hi>Affirmanti incumbit pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batio,</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. But,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pa.</hi> 39.</note> Sir, your plain diſtinction will not ſerve the preſent turne, it is this, we <hi>endeavour againſt Law when the things is Eſtabliſhed by Law, or cannot be Eſtabliſhed without Law:</hi> Pray Sir, is it againſt Law for Subjects, much more Legiſlators to endaevour the altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yea the abrogation, of ſome Laws and things thereby eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed; this is that your Antagoniſts affirm muſt be proved and brought into the concluſion to prove the matter of the Covenant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Law, and conſequently ſinful: May not an obedient Son of the Church, burdened with ſome Adminiſtration, authorized by Law, endeavour by all juſt means and ſwear he will ſo do, to have that Law repealed, if ſo how poor is your plain diſtinction.</p>
               <p n="4">4. But you doubt not to aſſert that ſuch an endeavour to Extri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate Church Government as was Covenanted was againſt the Law both Antecedent to the Covenant and ſubſequent, this done would much availe; we ſhall attend your evidence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="case">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:56201:17"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Caſe XI.</hi> Whether the preſent Government of the Church were Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by Law in <hi>England,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Caſe 11th. pa. <hi>41.</hi>
                  </note> before the taking of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</head>
               <p n="1">1. TO this, you profeſs you have no inſight into the Laws, but ſo much is in the ſurface of them, that you won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at the doubt; we do Sir, believe you; for in the Index of the ſtatute book, there is ſo large a Table of Biſhops, Arch-Biſhops, &amp;c. that it may well be wondred that any ſhould doubt whether this Government be eſtabliſhed by Law. But had you taken the pains to read and conſider the nature of the Laws, you would find <hi>Fronti nulla fides,</hi> your inſight would find wanting what a ſuperfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial verive of the ſurface concludeth preſent.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The fallacious uſe of, eſtabliſhed by law, is in your own fancy your Antagoniſts never did limit it to an appointment of Statute, but have traverſed the Canon, Civil and Common Law, and in none they find an eſtabliſhment by Law, but have put the aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors thereof to prove it, which task you have undertaken, and thus you argue.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Is it not pritty to obſerve that learned men ſhould be ſo far ſubdued by prejudice,<note place="margin">Pa. 42.</note> as to queſtion, whether Epiſcopacy be eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by Law, when Epiſcopacy hath ſo long had an hand in eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing the law it ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. This Argument hath, Sir, little force, we ſhall not be laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into a perſwaſion, that Epiſcopacy is eſtabliſhed by Law; and ſuch eſtabliſhment is a <hi>non ſequitur</hi> to the Legiſlative Act of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops; it cannot be both cauſe and effect, its praeexiſtency to the Law doth ſuppoſe unto it a more ſublime principle then the Law, which we know not unleſs it be that of Nature, or Scripture, or (as the Covenanters-plea doth well obſerve) the Romane Papacy, which forinſecal power exiſting in <hi>England</hi> as other Nations Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped a Legiſlative power, which it yet holdeth by this Epiſcopal root.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Sir, Would it not be pritty to hear a Jeſuite retort and prove
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:56201:18"/>your Argument, crying is it not pritty to obſerve learned men, and Prelates are ſo far ſubdued to queſtion whether the papacy were eſtabliſhed by Law, when the Papacie for a thouſand years eſtabliſhed yea made lawes to Chriſtian Nations, and diſpoſed their Crowns an Scepters; if laughing will do it the Papacy hath a good claim, and you ſeem to us to admit ſucceſſion in fact, a ſufficient title againſt the moſt manifeſt obtruſion, invaſion, and uſurpation which can be admitted.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Such Divines who found Monarchie in nature, and proclaim Monarchs to be above the Law, will give you little thanks for this Argument, which eſtateth their Title on an eſtabliſhment by law, becauſe they are chief makers of the Law; but you proceed to further demonſtration of an eſtabliſnment by law.</p>
               <p n="7">7. You ſay,<note place="margin">Pa. 43.44.</note> you will venture to ſtrike this ſcruple dead, by a diſtinction or two.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Your firſt diſtinction is this, <hi>The law eſtabliſheth by appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it</hi> de novo, <hi>or by allowing and granting it on all occaſions.</hi> The firſt you yeild; the ſecond you hold upon, and thus inferr, <hi>Thus the Law doth ſufficiently eſtabliſh the Government of the Church not onely by thoſe ſpecial lawes which relate unto it, but indeed in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry law which expreſſeth the conſent and advice of the Lords Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. A fair Eſtabliſhment, moſt lawes do indeed expreſs the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent and advice of the Lords Spiritual; we hope, Sir, you did not forget Lords-Abbots, and Lord Cardinal were ſome of them.</p>
               <p>But, Sir, is every Hypotheſis in law an undeniable poſition? Will Arguments, <hi>a facto,</hi> conclude <hi>ad jus?</hi> and <hi>ab eſſe a jure eſſe?</hi> and yet, Sir, this only concludes for Biſhops, what becometh of Deans and Chapters, Commiſſaries and Chanſellors, &amp;c. Are theſe Lords ſpiritual in the ſence of the Law; they do indeed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe a ſpiritual Lordſhip in the Church; Will an Argument from perſons of exiſtence in ſuch a capacity conclude an Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of things? Lords Spiritual were in Parliament, <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Government of the Church by Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, Deans, Chapters, and that Hyrarchie were eſtabliſhed by Law, will you ſtand by this Argument?</p>
               <p n="10">10. That Biſhops, or Lords Spiritual were in Parliament, <hi>De facto,</hi> is granted, but <hi>quo jure,</hi> is the queſtion, the Romans will
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:56201:18"/>tell you by the Popes Spiritual Power, and the Covenanters think how ever they are there preſerved they were firſt planted by that Forinſecal Power.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Your next Diſtinction is this;<note place="margin">Pa. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>This Government as to its office is before the Law, but as to its exerciſe it is Eſtabliſhed by Lawes, for its Names, Iuriſdictions Crimes and Puniſhments, are mentioned in the Lawes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. The firſt of theſe we allow you, but tell you that is the thing in debate, for the Eſtabliſhment of a Government is the Creation of ſuch an Office, in Execution of which, men ſhall have the Power, Titles, Names, and Honors of ſuch Officers: And herein your Government muſt be yielded to be the Popes Creatute; for we find no Engliſh lawes which ever framed or founded the ſame.</p>
               <p n="12">12. As to the Exerciſe of this Government in its way and order, by Courts, Canons and viſitations, we muſt tell you we find its names, Crimes and ſome puniſhments in our Lawes) yet we queſtion whether it were Eſtabliſhed by Law) becauſe we find theſe things are inſerted into our Lawes) to limit, regulate and reſtraine the ſame, which exiſting from a Forinſecal Power, grew exorbitant, and called for Boundaries, from our municipal lawes which rides it with a prohibition as its bridle, and ſcourg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it with a <hi>premunire;</hi> Both which Writts do know it to be a Power and Government diſtinct from that Eſtabliſhed by Law.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Sir, This is far from an Eſtabliſhment by Law, be not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended if we tell you Uſury hath as good an Eſtabliſhment by law as this amounteth unto, it is limited, regulated, reſtrained by law, and kept under the Cudgel of the Statutes againſt Extorti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But I pray you is it ſo eſtabliſhed by law, that the oppreſſed poor man may not ſwear, he will in his Place and Calling endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the Exſtirpation of biting Uſury or pinching Prelacy.</p>
               <p n="14">14. <hi>Your</hi> third <hi>Diſtinction is this Government Eſtabliſhed by a Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute immediately appointing ſuch a Forme,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag: <hi>45:</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>or immediately by a Statute impowring a Perſon to Commiſſionate ſuch Governours to the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">15. The firſt of theſe you grant, your Government hath not, nor do you prove the ſecond your Argument doth at moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude for Governours, and the Queſtion is about the Frame of Government: Your Proof is for Governors, indefinite, and we
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:56201:19"/>have told you the Supremacy of the King may exiſt in, and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate by, Church Governours under other Appellations; We do not ſay, men muſt Exſtirpate Governors, they may ſubſiſt, when their capacities are changed, but a full Eſtabliſhment of this Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Government by Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, &amp;c. we are as ready to ſeek, and as farr from finding now we have read your diſtinctions, as we were before.</p>
               <p n="15">15. What you urge concerning the Common Law, common uſage is ſo fully obviated by the Covenanters-Plea, that we ſhall ſay nothing to it; onely let us tell you; Preſcription is a poor Fence to Uſurpation, and a bad Guard for a Power in its <hi>origo</hi> manifeſtly Forinſecal. Uſury is a common uſage, yet no man will ſay, it is ſinful and againſt law; for men to ſwear in their Places and Callings, they will endeavour to exſtirpate an evil cuſtome though a common uſage.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="case">
               <head>
                  <hi>Caſe XII.</hi> Whether the Covenant taken firſt can oblige againſt a future Law?<note place="margin">Caſe <hi>12.</hi> Pa. <hi>47.</hi>
                  </note>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. IN this Caſe you urge an Eſtabliſhment of Epiſcopal Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, by a Law made ſince the Covenant was taken; But, Sir, you herein move upon a <hi>Petitio principii,</hi> and conclude what we muſt make bold to deny.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We have peruſed the late Statutes, and finde indeed Biſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ops reſtored to ſome priveledges which had been denyed to them, and this Government is guarded againſt ſome Batteries to which it was obnoxous, both theſe are ſpeciallities, under which the Government is left to ſtand on its old bottome, for it hath not received any more expreſs Eſtabliſhment then it had before; Now, Sir, if Uſery, ſhould by a new Law, be reſtored to Eight <hi>per Cent.</hi> we hope it had not acquired any new Eſtabliſhment which ſhould make the endeavour of its exſtirpation any more ſinful then before.</p>
               <p n="3">3. We muſt make bold to tell you, you read without book when you ſay <hi>this Government is Eſtabliſhed by the Act for Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:56201:19"/>that ſo much as endeavours of alteration are prohibited, &amp; Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are bound to declare, they may not ſo much as endeavour againſt it;</hi> For Sir ſimple endeavour is not by this Law prohibited, not is this to be declared againſt, which certainly were deſtructive to the liberty of the Subject, and priveledge of Parliament, who muſt have a freedome to the alteration of Laws as they prove in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenient.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This Law doth binde Miniſters to diſclaime a principle, not to diſavow a power in themſelves, to declare that the Covenant doth oblige to endeavour, not that endeavour ſhall be ſimply un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, they are not barred from lawful endeavours on good ground, and woful experience of the evil of this Government, but from improving the Covenant to provoke the ſame; from a ſpecial, to conclude generally, is no good Argumentation.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Your firſt propoſition failing, doth ſave us the labour of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſing the ſecond, how far an Oath may binde againſt Law; we ſhall only tell you that your Antagoniſts cry out that you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this alſo in our Caſe on a <hi>Petitio principii,</hi> taking for gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted what they deny, As:
<list>
                     <item>1. That this Governmet is in it ſelf Lawful, which they ſay is ſinful.</item>
                     <item>2. That inconveniences may not neceſſitate and warrant an alteration, and lawful endeavour to alter, or remove a thing in it ſelf lawful, and by Law Eſtabliſhed.</item>
                     <item>3. That this Oath was private and perſonal by fingle men, and ſo ſquare to the Caſe of your Jeſuites; which they ſay,<note place="margin">Analepſ. Analepth. <hi>Pa. 133.</hi> Sect <hi>6.</hi>
                        </note> and Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> as we before told you, hath averred to be publick and National, ſworn by the people Collectively, and Diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively conſidered.</item>
                     <item>4. That the Oath of the people ſo ſworn, layeth no barr on the Laws, Decrees, or Act of the Magiſtrate, the contrary whereto Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> hath aſſerted from the Oath of <hi>Iſrael</hi> hind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Sauls</hi> Law, and Oath againſt <hi>Ionathan,</hi> to which you have given nothing in anſwer, we think few Polititians will conclude the ſubjection of Political Children to be ſo fully and formally puerile, as you ſuppoſe it is.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. We, Sir, inſiſt not on theſe things, becauſe we undertake not to become your opponents, we only crave leave to let you
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:56201:20"/>know, Oaths are ſacred things and Poſt-laws are a ready Papacie to abſolve them, according to your Divinity, we have ſworn al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance to, and an acknowledgement of the Kings Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, and cannot be willing his Majeſties Subjects ſhould be made to beleive a Law by a Queen <hi>Marys</hi> Parliament will ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve their Conſciences and Oath. Yet we are not convinced that it is ſimply unlawful for Princes to give up their power, or part thereof unto ſome forreigne Potentate, but we for bear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe theſe ſtrings are not ſtruck with Prudence or Piety; Theſe affirmed ſound Atheiſm and Irreligion, theſe denied ſound Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or at leaſt Sedition.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="case">
               <head>
                  <hi>Caſe XIII.</hi> Whether ſubmitting to the Penalty annexed,<note place="margin">Caſe 13th Pa. <hi>60.</hi>
                  </note> be a due fulfilling or obeying the Law in the point of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</head>
               <p n="1">1. SIr, To what you urge againſt us in this Caſe, we ſay, Firſt you ſuppoſe that to be in the Law which we finde not to be in it, as we have before noted.</p>
               <p n="2">2. you ſtate your Caſe to narrow, when you confine it to a ſingle Act, of obedience to a ſingle Law, we well know who ſo ſuffers by a Law, ſuffereth as a tranſgreſſour of the Law, which is fulfilled by puniſhing him, whoſe Act was not conforme unto it; The Caſe, Sir, we conceive ought to be thus ſtated.</p>
               <p>Is not a quiet and chearful ſubmiſſion to the Penalty aſſigned by a Law commanding an Act which conſcience (judging ſinful) doth inhibit a formal Act of that Conſciencious obedience, Chriſtianity bindeth us to yeild to all Superiors.</p>
               <p>This Sir was the honour of the Chriſtian Leagions, that they were willingly led by droves to the Slaughter-houſe, and did not run into Mutinious and Rebelious routes, though armed with power when commanded to ſin, Chriſtians as Chriſt have a formal obedience unto the Croſs; This Sir is yet our Comfort, though we be tranſgreſſours to this ſingle Law, we are by Loyalty
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:56201:20"/>and ſincere obedience reſigned in the to will of our Soveraigne Lord the King, and Conſcience to do what is commanded, or cheerfully to ſuffer what is adjudged, is the ſecurity of human peace, and order.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="case">
               <head>
                  <hi>Caſe XIV.</hi> VVhether to endeavour the Exſtirpation of Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by virtue of the Covenant, notwithſtanding the Laws to the contrary,<note place="margin">Caſe 14th. Pa: <hi>67:</hi>
                  </note> be not againſt the Priviledge of Parliament and conſequently ſinful.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THis Sir you aſſirme, and about it make many words, which yet reach not the leaſt ſatisfaction to our minds becauſe you take for granted things denyed.</p>
               <p>Firſt, That the Covenant was an Oath private and perſonal; good Sir will you pleaſe to tell us, whether <hi>England</hi> is not a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject capable of a real Oath, as well as other Nations, conſider the nature of a real publick &amp; National Oath, may it not binde all Succeſſours to, or againſt ſome ſpecials? Was the Law of <hi>Saul,</hi> the Princes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> againſt the <hi>Gebeonits</hi> to be juſtifyed? Why ſhould they and all other Conventions of them be bound by the Oath of <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> and the Princes with him? Pray? Reſolve Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> that the Solemne League and Covenant is not <hi>Iuramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> real.</p>
               <p>Again, Sir, is the <hi>Conatus</hi> of a private capacity conſiſtent with the freedome of all Parliaments? This ſo pinched upon you that you are conſtrained to cry, then keep your Covenant, yet you call on us to declare we are not bound to endeavour.</p>
               <p>Sir, weigh well theſe two, that <hi>Conventus Anglorum</hi> may binde themſelves and ſucceſſours, and lawful endeavour is <hi>ſui juris</hi> to every man, and evince the Injuſtice or violence done to priveledge of future Parliaments if you can.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="case">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:56201:21"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Caſe XV.</hi> VVhether it be lawful to endeavour the Exſtirpation of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy by vertue of the Covenant,<note place="margin">Caſe 15th. Pa. <hi>74.</hi>
                  </note> notwithſtanding the Act of Parliament.</head>
               <p>IN this Caſe, Sir, we cannot but obſerve you do, <hi>Magno conatu ſudare de verbo,</hi> ſweat much at the Word Endeavour; endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to avoid it rather than underſtand or explain; After which you not only leave us unſatisfyed, but engaged more then you found us.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Sir, You cannot poſſibly deny but that there are more wayes of Endeavour then by Violence and Sedition, though you keep ſuch only in your eye, and have an heart ſo affected againſt the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, that you could wiſh there were no other; and ſeem pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched that your Antagoniſts do explain Places and Callings, to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Endevour to Acts juſt and lawful, Yet you are conſtrained to tell us to ſuch Endeavours the Covenant doth binde, and the Act doth not require us to diſclaime.</p>
               <p n="3">3. You have profeſſed to explain the meaning of this word <hi>Endeavour,</hi> and appear angry that none hath done it before, and yet you have not given us any Etimologie, Acception, or Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of the word; only you have pitched on ſome ſpecial Acts, by which endeavour may operate, which in the height of prejudice you improve to ſhew your diſſaffection to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant without giving the leaſt ſatisfaction to thoſe for whoſe ſake you profeſs you have written.</p>
               <p n="4">4. After all that is ſaid by you, we muſt enquire if any of the Acts of endeavour, you obſerved be lawful; or, if there be lawful Acts of endeavour, which you have not obſerved; Muſt we diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime them? Are not theſe poſitive duty? You have determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned theſe in the Affirmitive; But Sir, we will goe to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt: Is it no poſſible for thoſe very Acts which bear in your eyes the worſt aſpect to become lawful endeavours, <hi>(viz.)</hi> The Miniſter to preach, the Lawyer to plead, and the Souldier to fight againſt Epiſcopacy, if by any previous endeavours, King
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:56201:21"/>and Parliament can be perſwaded to exſtirpate this Government, and they make Laws to pluck it up, but its ſubjects are ſtubborne, and Rebell-raſing <hi>Bellum</hi> meer Epiſcopal, ſo that lawful Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity requireth theſe Acts, from theſe Agents in their places and Callings to the utmoſt of their power, and unto their lives end. Sir, the limitation of Endeavour in the Covenant is ſo ſquare to Reaſon and Religion, that rage may rend it Religious, reaſon can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not releaſe the Covenaters from it.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Sir that we may if poſſible obtain ſatisfaction, we ſhall give our apprehenſions of this Clauſe in the Covenant, that if you can evince our error or its ſinfulneſs, you may pleaſe to do it.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Sir, The words of the Covenant are theſe, <hi>Wee ſhall in like manner,</hi> that is, <hi>ſincerely, really, and conſtantly, through the Grace of God in our Places and Callings, endeavour the Extirpation of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy,</hi> viz. <hi>Church Government by Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, their Chauncellors and Commiſſionaries, Deanes, Deanes and Chapters, Arch-Deacons, and all other Eccleſiaſtical Officers depending on that Hierarchic.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. This promiſe containeth in it the Act Endeavour, the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject Exſtirpation, the quaile of the Act ſincerely, really, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, Through the Grace of God in our Places and Callings.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The Act is <hi>Endeavour,</hi> an Act general and indefinite, a word eaſy and plain to be underſtood, and of a large Significa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, an Act within the reach of every mans Arme, to be done by men in any Calling, or Capacity; and able to employ the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt power and skill, the Latin word is <hi>Conamen,</hi> or <hi>Conatus,</hi> the Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Temptation, and in the Hebrew <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> acquiſition by all or any means, it Signifieth a perſonal Act, the leaſt perſonal Act, and the utmoſt perſonal Act what we can, and all that we can do, it intendeth not the effect, but a motion towards the effect; the leaſt motion of our ſelves, and Natural power to that effect, a ſimple <hi>Conari</hi> to which <hi>Manibus pedibuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </hi> is an Adjunct like that in <hi>Terence, timet ne ſe deſeras p. egone iſtuc conari queam,</hi> I cannot ſo much as endeavour it, this is the Act promiſed generally and indefinitely, without thoſe ſpecial Acts by which it muſt operate.</p>
               <p n="9">9. This Act may be feeble feigned Language, and by ſinful
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:56201:22"/>means, It is therefore in the Covenant qualified with ſincerity, reallity, and conſtancy, ſuch as may be animated by the Grace of God, and muſt be lawful in our places and callings; So that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful Acts of Endeavours are abandoned, and all Hypocriſie, Luke-warmneſs, and Inconſtancy of Endeavour are to be avoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
               <p n="10">10.<note place="margin">Analepſ. Analepth. Pag: <hi>37:</hi>
                  </note> Upon the conſideration of the Act Endeavour, and its quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, We ſee not how Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> interpretation can be avoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; We have in the Covenant ſworn with very much caution, not to effect, but in our Places and Callings, to endeavour: But this muſt not be by a bare wiſh for purity, and then welcome corruption, a conſent to Reformation, and then a compliance with Superſtition, a faint refuſal, &amp; then free reception of the eſtate to be Exſtirpated, no it muſt be a ſtout and ſtrenuous endeavour, withal force and fervour, as Dr. <hi>Saunderſon</hi> in this caſe well no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth; <hi>Obligat hoc genus juramenti non ad effectum quem ſupponi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus eſſe impoſſibilem, ſed ad conatum quam dieu ſpes ulla ſuperat; imo quo plures &amp; majores abijeiuntur difficultates, eo abnixius co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandum, &amp; fortioribus annimis ob intendum eſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. You ſee, Sir, the promiſe in the Covenant explained; and it is plain that the Covenanted-endeavour is by the Declaration to be diſclaimed, nor will this diſclaimer admit of any ſence in which you endeavour to conſtrue it; the Covenant bindeth to a general and indefinite endeavour, yet this, Miniſters muſt as ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally and indefinitely diſclaim and declare againſt, which we (conſidering endeavour is <hi>ſui juris</hi> to the meaneſt Subject, and moſt private man; and this endeavo covenanted, muſt be order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and regular in their places, and callings; and Religious, through the Grace of God) cannot conſent to diſclaim and delare a <hi>non Obligation</hi> on them who ſwear it.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Sir, Having conſidered the Act, we bear ſuch affection to Epiſcopacy, that we would have paſſed by the Object of this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanted Act; You are pleaſed to tell us it is a change in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: By altering ſome things and letting the frame ſtand, not of the Government by pulling it down; And this ſence you ſay you gather from ſome moderate Covenanters, who openly declared on a ſolemn occaſion, that might they ſee any material alteration in the Government, they ſhould hold themſelves ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied as to the Covenant in that point,</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:56201:22"/>
               <p n="13">13. Sir, Can the Declaration of ſingle perſons though Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanters determine a ſence upon the Covenant, which the Logi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal reſolution, and Grammatical conſtruction of the words will not allow; We cannot but commend Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> Candor (be his Prudence what it will) nor do we ſee how his Interpretation can be fairly avoided, Prelacy (a terme though general in its ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification, yet by long and common appropriation as obvious to vulgar capacity to denote a ſpecial kind of Government in the Church, as Tyranny in the Common-Wealth.) reſtrained by a particular denomination, Hierarchy and ſpecifical deſcription of its enumerated parts, Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, Deans, Deans and Chapters, Commiſſaries, Chancellors, and other Officers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending thereupon, not in <hi>ſenſu compoſite</hi> (that the removeal of any one Officer might ſerve,) but <hi>ſenſu complexo</hi> the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment containing theſe is to be exſtirpated not by mutation, mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilation, limitation, or regulation, but utter abolition, <hi>una cum ſtirpe evellere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14. Sir, If the ſence of the Covenant were ſo far as you do ſuggeſt, we can the leſs declare its <hi>non obligation;</hi> for that is, to diſclaim what you cannot but on as good and true, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine it doth not bind, wherein it is manifeſt it doth bind thoſe who took the ſame, and your ſelf dare not deny its Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="case">
               <head>
                  <hi>Caſe XVI.</hi> Whether the Covenant be not against the Liberty of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject in this particular,<note place="margin">Caſe 16th Pa. <hi>89.</hi>
                  </note> and therefore ſinfull in its matter.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THis you affirme, and to make good your Argument, you tell us of the hard uſage the Biſhops met withal, being thrown out of the Houſe of Lords, &amp;c. But, Sir, What is this to the Covenant, they were thus uſed before the Covenant formed, and by the conſent of the King; if they met with In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice and Violence ſhall the Covenant be blamed, it bound to no ſuch thing, though to the an endeavor of Exſtirpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:56201:23"/>of the Government, by all juſt and lawful means.</p>
               <p n="2">2. You tell us the Biſhops and their dependents were a ſociety, had and their Free-holds and Intereſts. But, Sir, remember it was, <hi>Qua tales</hi> as Biſhops, and ſure, Sir, you will not deny this as all other ſocieties are fully, <hi>Sui Iuris,</hi> to Parliament, as to their very <hi>eſſe,</hi> as well as Juriſdiction or Adminiſtration, to be wholly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed at their will, and by their Power; We cannot beleive, Sir, you will in cooll blood, and on ſecond thoughts ſay, that for the King or Parliament to ſwear to Exſtirpate any ſociety, it is as if a man ſhould ſwear to bring me his Neighbours Horſe; Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> hath averred Epiſcopacy to be more fully and formally the Right of Parliament or King to diſpoſe of.</p>
               <p n="3">3. You ſay, The Petition of Right tells us, it is contrary to the Liberty of the Subject to have an Oath impoſed without an Act of Parliament; But, Sir, Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> hath told you and us, that the Petition of Right tells us no ſuch thing,<note place="margin">Annalepſ. Annalepth: Pa. <hi>115:</hi>
                  </note> he ſaith the words of the Petition ate theſe; Whereas many of them have had an Oath Adminiſtred unto them, not Warrantable by the Lawes and Statutes of this Realm; And he Affirmes this Petition com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineth of ſome ſpecial Oath, <hi>Ex officio,</hi> or for diſcovery of the Subjects Oath, he further tells us that Colledges and Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, conſtituted by the Kings Charter, give Oaths, which the Petion of Right complained not againſt, and yet they were not impoſed by Act of Parliament; We do not believe you will ſay theſe are againſt the Liberty of the Subject. Sir herein we muſt tell you your Argument is manifeſtly prevented by what Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> had ſaid, and ſo indeed in moſt that you have written on this, as on your other Caſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="case">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:56201:23"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Caſe XVII.</hi> Whether the matter of the ſecond Article in the Covenant be not againſt former Obligations,<note place="margin">Caſe 17th: Pa. <hi>98.</hi>
                  </note> and conſequently Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THis you affirm, and to prove it, you pretend to a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Obligation, to which the Covenant is repugnant, <hi>viz.</hi> To obey Authority, to keep our Oaths and Promiſes, and to ſerve the Church.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The firſt you build upon your former Principles, that the matter of the Covenant is againſt the Right of the King, the Laws of the Land, Priveledge of Parliament, and liberty of the Subject; which we conceive are all laid in the duſt, your Concluſion muſt needs fall with your Promiſes.</p>
               <p n="3">3. For the Oaths and Promiſes which were firſt upon us, you ſpecifie the Oath of Allegiance, Supreamacy, and the Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: 5 <hi>May</hi> 1641. In all which you are ſo fully prevented by Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> who hath noted them to be conſiſtent with the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, that we cannot but wonder you ſhould with ſuch confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence impoſe on us, without a full anſwer to what is ſaid by him.</p>
               <p n="4">4. One thing we muſt not paſs, <hi>viz.</hi> Your Obſervation that the Proteſtation, was impoſed by the ſame power, and taken by the ſame perſons, generally who took the Covenant, which is enough by Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> Logick, to make it publick and National; Sir, we believe Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> would not ſtick to allow you the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionality of the Proteſtation; yet we obſerve it wants one ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial thing in Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> account, neceſſary to conſtitute <hi>Iura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum reale,</hi> and therein it doth differ from the Covenant: The Proteſtation was ſworn with an <hi>I. A. B.</hi> by that perſonal name, which periſhed with the Takers thereof; but the Covenant was ſworn by thoſe real Capacities, Noble-men, Knights, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Citizens, Miniſters of the Goſpel, and Commons of all ſorts, which paſs, and will paſs to our Succeſſours, whilſt <hi>England</hi> is <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:56201:24"/>
               <p n="4">4. Your laſt Oligation is our ſervice to the Church, ſuperſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Covenant; But, Sir, you do not tell us whether it be Natural or by Accident, mans Corrupt nature interpoſing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween that Act and our Service to the Church. Sir, we conceive the beſt of Actions may be as capable of an <hi>Impeditivum boni,</hi> by the intervenient inhibiting Decree of <hi>Caeſar;</hi> and we are to be ſatisfied, that in that caſe, the guilt of non ſervice to the Church is chargaable on our Soul, we may not ſin that good ſhould come thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The Concluſion.</head>
               <p>VVE have,<note place="margin">Concluſion:</note> Sir, conſidered your great undertaking, to charge Sin on the matter of the Covenant, in which, Sir, we muſt ſay you have not ſpoken any thing of ſatisfaction to us, nor Rational contradiction to thoſe whom you pretend to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Finding the matter of the Covenant lawful, we are not ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitous concerning the Mode of its impoſition; we could eaſily declate what in that Caſe is required from us; We therefore not appearing as your Antagoniſts, but ſeeking ſatisfaction to our main doubt, which is, how we can declare the Covenant doth not oblige us nor any other perſon to Endeavour, ſhall abide wholly ſilent as to your next three Caſes concerning the Act and power of the two Houſes, the unlawfulneſs of the Oath, and illegality of the Impoſition.</p>
               <p n="3">3. We are, Sir, ſorry to ſee you ſo obnoxious in many expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, to correction of your Antagoniſts, if any of them durſt be ſo hardy as to undertake an anſwer to you, as indeed you are; But, Sir, this is not our work, we are ſatisfied in our ſelves, that howſoever men count us, <hi>Fures, Felones,</hi> and Proditors, <hi>de ſe,</hi> we can appeal to our Judge, Conſcience is the cauſe of our choice of that ſad condition in which we are; Whilſt we can conclude with that learned Caſniſt the late Reverend Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln, Jura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum de re non illicita, fit aliunde illicitum, ex aliquo externo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectu, vel propter aliquam indebitam circumſtanſtiam reſpectu actus jurandi poſſit obligare, jurantem ad implendum quod promiſit:</hi>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:56201:24"/>though we were not advancers of the Covenant, when firſt impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, though we are no Advocates for the Covenant to be diſclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, we are Expectants of Gods avengement of the Covenant now it hath been taken; and do beleive it is preſumption, <hi>Non ferenda quod pulvis &amp; cinis aſſumeret poteſtate in auferendi obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem qua home obligatur Deo:</hi> We therefore yet dare not, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, will not declare the Covenant doth not oblige me or any other perſon to endeavour our alteration of the Government in the Church, But if you have more clear demonſtrations that we may ſo do; We have attention and conſideration for the ſame, we are, Sir,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your Brethren praying for the Peace, though not conforming to the whole, of the order of</hi> Englands <hi>Church.</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>M. D.</item>
                        <item>S. C.</item>
                        <item>I. F.</item>
                        <item>O. R.</item>
                        <item>A. T.</item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
                  <date>Oct. 16. 1662.</date>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
